this section is going to be the chapter
1 and overview of the active inference
textbook
so shown here are the table of contents
there are 10 chapters and three
appendices in this book and they're
separated into part one with chapters
one through five and part two chapters
six through ten Ali do you want to give
any overview thoughts on the
organization or structure of the book
okay so
um
uh can you hear me now sorry yes okay so
part one is basically a more line
in terms of the theoretical
construction of the active inference and
it provides some conceptual and
theoretical uh tools to be utilized in
the second part uh because uh for the
second part we're mostly we mostly deal
with the Practical side of active
inference how to actually Implement
active inference to model uh some of the
systems of Interest so that's basically
the main justification behind dividing
up these chapters into two
great all right we're going to pass over
the short preface written by Carl
friston but it's worth a read it's only
several pages long so let's go to
chapter one overview so do you have any
opening thoughts on chapter one or where
does one even begin with such a book
sure uh yeah for chapter one I think uh
probably the most central theme of
chapter one is about the two different
approaches to active inference namely
the high road and the low road and I
think it provides a really nice
perspective to view a kind of the whole
picture and how the different components
of active inference fit together
so but
um also I I highly recommend uh chapter
13 from this book Andy Clark and it's uh
and Andy Clark and his critics written
by
chapter 13 I think is entitled beyond
the desert landscape written by Carl
Preston in which he provides a more
elaborate and a bit philosophical
reasoning behind what exactly are low
roads and how high road and what are the
aims of each approach and the
distinction between those two so
for chapter one we began obviously with
an introductory paragraph which sets the
stage for uh the I mean all the
components that would be discussed in
this chapter or so but a very important
section I believe is section two here
which is how do living organisms persist
and act adaptively which is basically
the main question active inference is
trying to address
so if we want to uh
describe active inference in uh I mean
minimalistically with only one sentence
or two uh probably we can say something
to the effect that it's a theory that
address this very question here
so I why they've opened up this chapter
with the important
question and then action three
which is again a continuation of section
one but a bit more specifically about
active inference and how active
inference is
addressing uh the question uh provided
in the section two so
uh basically again active inference is a
modeling framework for modeling the
behaviors from first principles and
what is meant by first principles will
be elaborated upon in the following
chapters and the following sections and
also I'll be using the following
chapters
but very briefly uh it's a kind of
modeling framework that tries to somehow
use
variational principles such as free
energy principle to uh to construct
modeling and mathematical tools that
will enable us to
um
to describe a dynamical systems of
living and even non-living agents in
terms of those variational principles
and how those agents or those systems
are coupled with their environment
so that's basically the
unificatory principle that is at the
heart of this active inference approach
because uh yes exactly here
it's a kind of description of this
action perception Loop that is at the
heart of active inference or fep
framework
and then we go to
chapter sorry section 1.4 which is again
a description of the structure of the
book and why those two parts are divided
as such
so as I said earlier first part is more
uh concerned with the theoretical
underpinnings of active inference and
the second part is more about the
Practical side of it as we see in these
subsection headings here
so that's uh
yeah and then
a very important diagram
which will provide very helpful as we
call book is provided in figure 1.2
which kind of uh ties all the different
strands of various related theories such
as predictive coding predictive
processing Bayesian brain hypothesis and
so on into a kind of unified and
integrated framework by using those two
trajectories of
constructing active inference namely the
high road and the low road
so it literally here is represented as
the high road and the low road in this
diagram
so very briefly uh
high road is a kind of top down approach
to active in Prince it begins with the
question
how and how things should act if they
exist in other word if they persist
through time sorry in other words
it kind of sets sets the stage for
developing the concept of markup
blankets
uh and then uh obviously with by uh
setting then also
um surprise minimization
uh it attempts to
elaborate that
um Road by adding other aspects of
modeling other aspects of theory such as
predictive processing self-evitancing
auto-poiesis and so on and then reach an
integrated version of active inference
which is basically an integration
between perception and action so uh
I believe the main thing that sets
active inference apart from all the
other related theories such as
predictive processing and predictive
coding is the very in deep integration
of action and perception so action is
not just
um some afterthought or some additional
component that needs to be accounted for
it is deeply woven into uh the fabric of
the theory so as we'll see especially in
chapters two and three
even the mathematical formalism for
perception and action
are interestingly similar to each other
and even symmetric and it shows that uh
perception and action are actually not
uh separate and distinct totally
distinct entities and Concepts and
um active inference uh definitely
provides a very promising framework to
integrate them into a holistic framework
and another approach to construct that
same theory is to begin with the
probabilistic description uh a base
theorem and
um try to build up
the formalism map active inference using
uh Bayes inference theorem theorem and
Bayesian statistical inference so again
we hear a system
very
um I mean apparently different and
distinct strands such as predictive
coding Bayesian brain hypothesis and so
on but as we see all of those different
strands can be United and tied together
with uh within this low road approach to
active inference
so
um
I guess that's uh I'll just give one
short thought thanks these are great
yeah just one short thought thank you
Ali for these great summaries
the low road and the high road are going
to be explored in a lot more detail in
the coming chapters two and three
we can think of the high road as being a
y
because it describes how persistent or
re-measurable systems exist now they
might be using base theorem or they
might be using any other kind of
mechanism internally but the high road
is describing the why of existence
from the low road the bottom-up approach
is kind of like a how you could use
Bayes theorem to describe persistent
Auto poetic entities
or you could use Bayes theorem for other
purposes too so where these two roads
intersect is active inference and we
have a lot more discussion coming and of
course unpacked in the textbook groups
about how these really map onto bottom
up and top-down causation and the
plurality of y's that we approach in
different settings
good to continue
yes sure
some of the coming sections uh of this
chapter continuing from page eight are
going to describe what are happening in
the next chapters so chapter two is
going to set out the low road
perspective
chapter 3 is going to describe the high
road chapter four we will unpack active
inference more formally that's one of
the math heavy chapters
chapter 5 will move from formal
treatments to biological implications of
active inference with a special focus on
mammalian neurophysiology
chapter 5 sets out the process Theory
associated with active inference and
gives a lot of Hands-On and empirical
examples and that's a lot of the first
part of the book
they're then going to summarize some of
the key points and distillations from
that theory heavy first section one of
them is that as Ali mentioned perception
and action are complementary processes
and ways that fulfill the same
imperative free energy minimization we
sometimes summarize that by saying that
in the pursuit of the minimization of
free energy agents can either change
their mind or change the world change
your mind is associated with perception
and learning
and those are distinguished later
and changing the world is associated
with action
there's some discussion about action
selection and optimal policy selection
and all cognitive operations in active
inference are conceptualized as
inference over generative models so the
true kernel the cognitive kernel of
active inference is going to be the
generative model
want to pick up from here or give any
thoughts on generative models and then
carry on thanks Ali
just one point is uh there is a common
misconception about generative models
which is that a generator models only
refers to this the interstates of the
system and also its markup blanket but
actually generative model kind of
Encompass all the states of interest
of the situation we're trying to model
so it also encodes the problem the
probabilistic information about the
external States as well so generative
model can be thought of as a kind of
the whole state of the system and by
System here I mean uh the coupled
um the couple says um a couple Dynamics
between the internal and external States
so uh that might be helpful to keep in
mind look
great one other distinction that comes
up and is used a lot nowadays although
it's not always used in Prior literature
is the distinction between the
generative model and the generative
process we're going to come back to it
but usually
the generative model is being used to
describe our statistical model of the
agent of interest and the generative
process is the process that generates
observations that are then passed to the
generative model as observations however
because generative models can be
generative processes for each other
these two are not necessarily distinct
in principle so in different simulations
and in different specific cases
generative models can also be generative
processes for each other that leads us
towards talking about ecosystems of
shared intelligence and interactions
amongst generative models but when we're
talking about generative model it's like
the organism or the system of interest
that we're focused on
there are some more uh themes that arise
from the first half of the book now
we're on page 11. action is
quintessentially goal directed and
purposes of we talk a lot about how
preference plays a role in shaping
action selection and active inference
and the goal-directed nature of active
inference will be unpacked in chapters
two and three
they discuss how various constructs of
active inference have plausible
biological analogs in the brain
once one has defined a specific
generative model for a problem at hand
one can move from active inference as a
normative Theory to active inference as
a process Theory which makes specific
empirical predictions and there's many
many interesting philosophy of science
type discussions that we have about
explain predict design control
and then we get to section 1.4.2 giving
overview on part two active inference in
practice
so I'll just continue on chapter 6 is
going to introduce a recipe for building
active inference models so this is where
the step-by-step comes into play
it's going to give a sequence of of
steps and approaches that you can take
to go from
understanding the structural aspects of
a system or phenomena of interest and
build your way towards having an active
inference model that can then be
implemented in code and we have various
examples and we're there in the textbook
group to work with everyone who wants to
take this journey but chapter six is
going to describe that process of
building the active inference generative
model so that's a recipe chapter and
there's a lot more that goes into the
restaurant also as we kind of have fun
exploring
chapter 7 and 8 are like a pair and they
describe two different broad families of
generative models now these two families
of generative models they work well they
play well with each other but they are a
very educationally relevant to also
consider separately chapter seven is
going to focus on the discrete time
generative model
and chapter 8 is going to focus on the
continuous time generative models and
again these discrete and continuous time
models can be nested and interoperable
however they do describe some very
important different situations and so
chapter seven and eight have a lot of
technical information on the discrete
and continuous time formulations of
active inference and also about how they
integrate together
chapter 9 is illustrations of how active
inference models can be used to analyze
data from behavioral experiments and so
this kind of goes beyond chapter six's
recipe and it talks about some of the
process of making a behavioral
experiment and then using the outcomes
of that behavioral experiment the data
from that experiment and using that to
parameterize and do statistics with the
active inference generative model
in chapter 10 brings it all together
chapter 10 is a lot like chapter one and
we've even joked of reading the book
backwards that's how great chapter 10 is
so for those who are reading chapter one
consider reading chapter 10 next and
then picking back up with chapter two
because chapter 10 is going to give some
judgments and also sketch some exciting
future directions for where active
inference is in relationship to other
fields and where it's going
so I also second that yeah
uh the second part of the book
illustrates a broad variety
of models of biological and cognitive
phenomena so it's an application
oriented second half of the book and we
have a lot of accessory code and
approaches and notebooks so one may not
find that this is the One-Stop shop that
they were looking for however for those
who dive in there's absolutely more than
enough to scaffold their Learning
Journey
um and then section 1.5 is the summary
the chapter introduces the active
inference approach to explain biological
problems from a normative perspective
and preview some implications of this
perspective that will be unpacked in
later chapters
it describes the structural outline of
the book chapters one through five being
Theory chapter 6 through 10 being
practice
and then it signals that the next two
chapters are going to develop the low
and the high road perspectives
and all together
that is chapter one any other thoughts
on chapter one
uh not specifically but I think it
provides a really good context to the
rest of the book in terms of how all the
different elements of active imprints
comes into play in addressing different
problems different problems
awesome